<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>fibbl</title>
    <link href="https://blog.fibbl.in/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.fibbl.in" />
    <updated>2022-04-09T05:39:42+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Anurag</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.fibbl.in</id>

    <entry>
        <title>What is an Emergency Fund?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anurag</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.fibbl.in/are-you-ready-for-an-emergency/"/>
        <id>https://blog.fibbl.in/are-you-ready-for-an-emergency/</id>
            <category term="Personal Finance"/>

        <updated>2022-04-09T05:39:35+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    How often has life caught us off-guard? Remember all the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/Emergency.png" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/responsive/Emergency-xs.png 300w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/responsive/Emergency-sm.png 480w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/responsive/Emergency-md.png 768w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/responsive/Emergency-lg.png 1024w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/responsive/Emergency-xl.png 1360w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/4/responsive/Emergency-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="" width="1640" height="924"></figure>
<p class="p3">How often has life caught us off-guard? Remember all the times when life threw real sour lemons at us and we were unable to lemonade them? It doesn’t take a genius to guess that the only certainty in life lies in its uncertainty. And while so many things that happen to us are beyond our control there is one thing that is totally in our hands. Facing every contingency that life has in store for us with an Emergency Fund!</p>
<p><strong>Why an Emergency Fund you ask? </strong></p>
<p>This fund is second in line to protect you against financial uncertainties. The first is your life/ health insurance. But not everything can be insured. For instance, your monthly rent payment. And you do not want to ask friends and family for a pecuniary favour or break your long-term investments for that matter.</p>
<p class="p5"><strong>Where to keep Emergency Fund?</strong></p>
<p>Experts suggest that you should maintain an Emergency Fund that covers at least 6-months of your basic expenses. This fund should be highly liquid with no risks attached. Hence, your options here include keeping the funds in cash, savings account, fixed deposit (FD), and liquid mutual funds.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cash</strong> – Cash is well, cash. Yes, that cash in your wallet is your Emergency Fund. The catch here is you are not supposed to burn this cash. You need to keep it safe and use it only in an emergency. So set aside some amount of cash from your wallet to some other wallet that is out of your daily reach.</li>
<li><strong>Savings account</strong> – Here again, create a separate savings account or earmark some amount in your regular savings account or create a recurring deposit (RD), and DO NOT use it until you are in a fix.</li>
<li><strong>Fixed Deposit–</strong> This is your deposit with a bank against which you get a fixed interest. The FD rates are higher than savings account interest rates. Long-term FDs (5 years or more) provide higher interest. Do note that premature withdrawal of money from FD attracts a penalty.Different banks provide different interest rates. Please check with your banker the interest rate that your bank provides. Also, it makes little sense to keep hopping from one bank to the other to simply earn 1-2% extra interest income.</li>
<li><strong>Liquid mutual funds</strong> – Allow me to break to you another certainty - your hard-earned money will die a slow (or not so-slow?) death. We often call it inflation. It is here that liquid mutual funds prove to be the most beneficial. They may or may not be able to beat inflation, but they will in all likelihood give you a return at par with inflation. These may, however, take up to 1-2 working days to be liquidated. </li>
</ul>
<p class="p5">You may also want to keep your tax expense in mind. The tax laws of our country change every year. As of now, redemption of debt mutual funds after 3 years (long-term capital gain) attracts a 20% tax rate with indexation benefit. Interest from savings account is not taxed up to INR 10,000, post which it is taxed at slab rates Interest from FD is taxed at slab rates. Cash, of course, is not taxed at all.</p>
<p class="p5">One can choose from any of the options listed above to maintain an Emergency Fund. You may choose to deposit some funds in all of these in varying proportions. Do remember, the idea here is not to make/ grow money, but to have some money handy should we need it one day. </p>
<p class="p5">Should couples decide to go for a joint Emergency Fund? If you guys get along well, you may want to sync your financial life as well. You may decide to have two separate Emergency Funds but make sure you discuss your household expenses and have regular money conversations with each other.</p>
<p>So, make a budget, keep a check on your and your partner’s unnecessary expenses (make sure you don’t become too nosy) and gradually make an Emergency Fund your future self will thank you for. Although we seriously hope that you never find yourself in a situation like that.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Deciphering- Joint Term Insurance vs Two Separate Term Plans</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anurag</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.fibbl.in/deciphering-joint-term-insurance-vs-two-separate-term-plans/"/>
        <id>https://blog.fibbl.in/deciphering-joint-term-insurance-vs-two-separate-term-plans/</id>
            <category term="Personal Finance"/>

        <updated>2022-04-09T05:39:42+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Insurance can be tricky to understand. But that can’t be&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/Add-a-subheading.png" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/responsive/Add-a-subheading-xs.png 300w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/responsive/Add-a-subheading-sm.png 480w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/responsive/Add-a-subheading-md.png 768w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/responsive/Add-a-subheading-lg.png 1024w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/responsive/Add-a-subheading-xl.png 1360w ,https://blog.fibbl.in/media/posts/3/responsive/Add-a-subheading-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Insurance" width="1640" height="924"></figure>
<div class="zw-paragraph heading1" data-width="601" data-header="1" data-textformat="{&quot;size&quot;:10}">
<div class="zw-line-div">
<div class="zw-line-content align-center"><span class="zw-portion" data-text-len="1"><span class="zw-space">   </span></span></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="zw-paragraph" data-width="601" data-textformat="{&quot;size&quot;:10}"> </div>
<div class="zw-paragraph heading105" data-width="601" data-header="105" data-textformat="{&quot;size&quot;:10}">
<div class="zw-line-div">
<div class="zw-line-content">
<div class="zw-paginated zw-page">
<div class="zw-pagecontainer">
<div class="zw-contentpane selectableSection">
<div class="zw-column-container">
<div class="zw-column">
<div class="zw-paragraph" data-width="601" data-textformat="{&quot;size&quot;:10}">
<div class="zw-line-div">
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Insurance can be tricky to understand. But that can’t be an excuse to ignore it, for insurance can be a life saviour – not your life, your loved ones’ lives! In this blog post, we decode a relatively new concept of </span><strong>joint term insurance</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and help you better understand the nitty-gritties of it. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let’s clear the basics first.</span></p>
<p><strong>What is term insurance?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Term insurance provides financial protection to your family against a fixed premium paid for a specified term. It is a pure risk cover form of life insurance. Pure risk cover implies that the insurance company doesn’t have to splurge out the sum assured if the insured survives the policy term. Because you let go maturity benefits, term insurance policies usually demand less premium than other forms of insurance. And once the premium amount is set, it remains the same. This also makes it an effective hedge against rising inflation.</span></p>
<p><strong>What is joint term insurance?</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Joint term insurance is a type of term insurance policy that covers </span><strong>two people</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> but pays out once. The pay-out can be made upon the death of -</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">the first partner (first-to-die life insurance) – the pay-out is made to the surviving partner, allowing the surviving partner to maintain his/ her lifestyle, or</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">both the partners (second-to-die life insurance) – the pay-out benefit goes to the couple’s beneficiaries who can be the couple’s children, relatives or anyone else. This joint term insurance can prove to be a great estate planning instrument.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The sum assured may be received as -</span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">regular payments for a fixed term, or-</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">a lump-sum payment, ending the policy there, or</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">as a combination of lump-sum and regular payments</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the above, <strong>why should couples choose joint term insurance over two separate term plans?</strong></span></p>
<p><strong style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">1. Economically viable:</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">Term insurance is generally more economical than other forms of insurance. Joint term insurance can prove to be even more affordable. With separate covers, insurance companies face a likely pay-out of say INR 50,00,000 as against a joint term insurance where the pay-out will be half of INR 50,00,000. Hence, the coverage offered under joint term insurance is less expensive vis-à-vis 2 separate insurance covers.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">2. Tax savings (that too twice)-</span></strong></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Section 80C of the Income-Tax Act (the Act), 1961 allow premium paid to be deducted from total income thereby bringing down your taxable income and taxes thereon. It is worth keeping in mind that only the partner who actually pays the premium will be allowed a deduction under these sections.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The pay-out received upon the death of the insured is exempt under section 10(10D) of the Act, i.e., the pay-out is not even considered as income in the first place.</span></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;"><br></span></strong><strong>3. Minimal hassle- </strong></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">It goes without saying that a single policy can be managed more easily than two separate policies. There is less paperwork involved, any one of the partners can pay the premium on behalf of the two of them, and both partners can access the policy account and keep a track of it jointly/ severally. Isn’t it great for planning your finances as a team?</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">4. Great for young couples-</span></strong></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">Death is inevitable. But young people have age by their side. The odds of them passing away during the insurance term are stacked against them. Which is why buying two insurance policies, when they can buy just one but enjoy the benefits of two, makes little sense. Young couples can pay less premium for a large sum assured in case of a joint term insurance policy.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><strong>5. Riders-</strong></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">A rider is an insurance policy provision that amends the terms of a basic insurance policy to provide additional coverage. In other words, riders help create customised insurance policies. Joint term insurance plans are available with riders which help couples to tweak their policies to suit their needs.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"><strong>6. Estate planning</strong>-</span></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">Second-to-die life insurance can help in the estate planning needs of couples. However, this arrangement is best suited with a whole life insurance policy. This is because if the insurance term ends before the passing away of the second holder, the policy lapses and the beneficiaries receive nothing.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">7. Standard of living-</span></strong></div>
<div class="zw-line-div"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">By receiving the pay-out upon the death of a partner, joint term policies can help the surviving partner maintain his/ her lifestyle.</span>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Insurance policies go a long way in keeping you and family financially secure. It is the first and strongest shield against any uncertainty that life throws at you. Understand your money needs, check with your agent and take the right step towards your and your family’s well-being.</span></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
